Contact

303-909-7318 (Work) kim@self-careacademy.com

www.linkedin.com/in/ recruitmentretentionresiliency (LinkedIn) self-careacademy.com (Company) krichardsassociates.com (Company)

Top Skills

Perioperative

Healthcare

Motivational Speaking

Languages

English

Spanish (Professional Working)

Certifications

American Council of Exercise Group Fitness

Board Certified Nurse Coach

Publications

Richards, K., The Disease of Busyness, Nursing Economic\$/ March-April 2015/Vol. 33/No. 2

Richards, K. Self-Care is a Lifelong Journey*, Nursing Economic\$/ July-August 2013/Vol.31.No.4. pp.198-202.

Nurses: To care for others, we must FIRST care for ourselves (Part One), Reflections of Nursing Leadership

Shiparski L, Richards K, Nelson J, Self-Care Strategies to Enhance Caring. Nurse Leader, June 2011, Volume 9, Issue 3: 26.

Richards, K,(2012) The Practice of Self-Care to Prevent Burnout and Create the Optimal Healing Environment. Mastering Precepting: A Nurse's Handbook for Success, ed. Beth Ulrich. Indianapolis, IN: Sigma Theta Tau International.

Kim Richards, RN, NC-BC

President at Kim Richards and Associates, Inc.

United States

Summary

I am an experienced recruitment and retention expert. I'm an author on the topic of resiliency, inspiring speaker, and a thriving life coach. I help individuals, teams, groups and corporations do three things:

1) permanently shift their culture toward improved resiliency and productivity 2) implement effective recruitment and retention strategies 3) Improve engagement and safety.

My career is diverse. I began as a critical care nurse, spent time in the pharmaceutical industry and In 1989, combining my nursing background with sales and marketing, I founded a successful executive recruitment firm. I have spent the past 15 years studying the science of self-care and resiliency as the foundation for living a purposeful, passionate life. I truly believe that healing ourselves is pivotal to creating a life of service to others.

Self-Care Academy

I founded Self-Care Academy®, my premiere speaking platform in 2005, with the desire to provide evidence based information on the power of lifestyle choices to boost energy, manage stress and reduce risk of most diseases.

My programs, keynotes and retreats:

- --improve engagement, effectiveness and productivity
- --inspire and motivate
- --lead to better individual resiliency
- --reduce absenteeism and burnout
- --decrease insurance premiums
- --create healthy work environment

NurseFit

NurseFit is designed to help nurses build their own "Self-Care Toolbox" allowing them to:

--build the emotional and mental resilience to perform at intense levels of stress

- --celebrate the connection between their work and their higher calling.
- --prevent Compassion Fatigue

Individual Coaching

With a 360 degree approach, I help people explore the root cause of "dis-ease" and support their journey to creating the life they dream of. My whole health programs create sustainable self-care practices that prevent or manage chronic disease.

Experience

Kim Richards and Associates, Inc.

31 years

President

September 2005 - Present (14 years 10 months)

National

Experienced, dynamic and results oriented healthcare leader for over 30 years. Nationally recognized author, speaker and expert in strategies to attract, retain and create a thriving culture for top talent. Recognized expert and servant leader in improving engagement, production and teamwork. Proven ability and professional business acumen to navigate a sophisticated and complex environment. More than 100 nurse executive searches successfully executed, with 100% placement, and 100% retention after one year.

Owner

1989 - Present (31 years)

Attract top talented nurse leaders

Self Care Academy, LLC

President

December 2005 - Present (14 years 7 months)

Internationally known inspiring speaker, author and expert in creating highly resilient, engaged and productive teams that learn to burn brightly without burning out. Successful in creating self-care/stress reduction strategies, leading workshops on caring for the caregiver and creating optimal healing environments. Fitness and yoga instructor, integrative/complimentary therapy, healthy lifestyle coach. Expert on topics such as Compassion Fatigue and Burnout in caregivers. Adjunct Faculty, International Integrative Nurse Coach Association.

Regular column contributor to professional journals such as Nursing Economics and Nurse Leader.

25+ years in executive healthcare recruitment industry. Focus on interim and perm placement for Perioperative nursing leadership. Recruitment, retention and culture change expert including strategies for creation of healthy work environment.

promote lifestyle changes to improve wellness and health

AORN Management Solutions, Inc.
General Manager
August 2002 - June 2005 (2 years 11 months)

Education

International Integrative Nurse Coaching Program ANCC Board Certified Nurse Coach, Integrative Nurse Coaching · (2010 - 2018)

American Council of Exercise

Certificate, Group Fitness / Yoga Instructor · (1996 - 2018)

Columbia Basin College Registered Nursing/Registered Nurse · (1978 - 1979)

Watts School of Nursing Nursing · (1976 - 1978)